Stigmochelys pardalis	Description (babcocki): “The largest species in Botswana, this tortoise may be distinguished by the absence of the nuchal shield (a single scute directly above the anterior opening of the carapace). The carapace is highly domed. The laminae of the carapace may be raised, and the marginals flared, or the carapace may be fairly smooth. Tawny yellow to brown with dark areolae. In juveniles there are usually dark margins on the scutes of the carapace enclosing dark spots, but as the tortoise grows, the dark markings change to form varying patterns, often breaking into spots or striations.” (Auerbach 1987: 67)Size: “FitzSimons (1935a:304) records a specimen from Maun with a carapace length of 302 mm. Lengths of 600 mm and masses of up to 40 kg have been recorded from South Africa (Archer 1968). Average 10-15 kg. Hatchlings about 30-35 g.” (Auerbach 1987: 67)Geochelone elegans	Description (genus s.l.): This is the largest genus of tortoises, both in number of living species (21) and in size attained (to 130 cm, and over 185 kg). It is pantropical with living species in Africa, Madagascar, India, Sri Lanka, Southeast Asia, Indonesia, South America, and on the oceanic Aldabra and Galapagos Islands. Formerly the genus was even more widespread, as fossil species are known from North America as far north as southern Canada, the British Isles, western Europe, northern Africa, the Middle East, Central Asia, and additional islands in the Indian Ocean (Auffenberg, 1974). Fossil Geochelone have even been found on Ellesmere Island (78°N) (Estes and Hutchison, 1980). No adults are less than 25 cm in carapace length. The hingeless carapace varies in shape from oval to elongated, and from domed to somewhat dorsally flattened (especially in males of some species) to saddlebacked (narrower and elevated anteriorly, wider and lower posteriorly). Some form of cervical indentation or notch is usually present, and the anterior marginals may be flared or downturned. Both anterior and posterior marginals may be serrated. Usually 11 marginals lie on each side of the carapace, and the supracaudal is usually single and undivided. There are no submarginal scutes, but a cervical scute is present in most species. The anterior neurals are alternately octagonal or quadrilateral in shape, and usually two suprapygal bones are present: the larger anterior suprapygal bifurcates posteriorly and partially surrounds the smaller posterior. The plastron lacks a hinge and varies from narrow to broad. Its posterior notch may be deep, shallow, or nonexistent. The thickened gular scutes are paired and broader than long in all species but Geochelone yniphora, which has them fused into a long single element; the entoplastron is almost always anterior to the humeropectoral seam. Axillary and inguinal buttresses are short, and barely touch the costals. The skull is short to moderate with a hooked, sometimes bior tricuspid upper jaw. Sides of the upper jaw are usually serrate. The triturating surface of the maxilla is strongly ridged, but no medial ridge occurs on the premaxilla. The maxillae do not contribute to the roof of the palate, and the anterior orbito-nasal foramina are small and concealed from ventral view. The temporal arch is weak to moderately wide. The prootic bone is well exposed dorsally and anteriorly, and the quadrate bone usually encloses the stapes. The limbs are club shaped with no toe webbing; each forefoot has five claws. In a few species, the tail ends in a large horny scale. (Ernst & Barbour 1989)Indotestudo elongata	Description (genus): Indotestudo is usually regarded as a subgenus of Geochelone (Auffenberg, 1974); however, considerable evidence has accrued that indicates it should be considered a separate genus. Charles R. Crumly, who has acted as our advisor on tortoise systematics, has completed morphological studies which indicate nine major differences (Table 5), and we follow his suggestion to elevate Indotestudo to full generic rank. The two medium-sized Asiatic tortoises belonging to Indotestudo occur in southern peninsular India, northeastern India, Nepal, and Bangladesh southward to Vietnam and Thailand, and on Celebes and Halmahera, Indonesia. The hingeless, low carapace is usually elongated, flattened dorsally, has a cervical notch, and the posterior marginals may be somewhat serrated. The anterior neurals are alternately octagonal or four sided. There are usually two suprapygal bones separated by a transverse suture; the anterior is larger than the posterior and partially surrounds it just as in most Geochelone and Gopherus. Usually, 11 marginals lie on each side of the carapace; the supracaudal is single and undivided. No submarginal scutes are present. A narrow cervical is present in one species. The hingeless plastron is well developed with a posterior notch so deep it may completely separate the anal scutes. The paired gulars are somewhat thickened, but not greatly projecting. The humero-pectoral sulcus usually crosses the entoplastron. Axillary and inguinal buttresses are short but strong, just extending to the costals. The skull is short to moderate with a hooked, usually tricuspid upper jaw. Sides of the jaws are somewhat serrated. Triturating surfaces of the maxillae usually have a weak to moderate medial ridge, but no ridge occurs on the premaxillae. The maxillae do not contribute to the roof of the palate, and the anterior orbito-nasal foramina are small and concealed in ventral view. The temporal arch is relatively weak. The prootic bone is typically well exposed dorsally and anteriorly; the quadrate encloses the stapes. Limbs are clublike; five claws occur on each fore-foot. The tail ends in a large horny scale. (Ernst & Barbour 1989)Recognition: The elongated carapace (to 27.5 cm) is domed, but flattened dorsally with descending sides, has a shallow cervical notch, a long narrow cervical scute, and the posterior marginals somewhat flared and serrated (more strongly serrated in juveniles). Vertebral 1 is about as broad as long, but 2-5 are broader than long; the 5th is expanded. Well-defined growth annuli surround the flat vertebral and pleural areolae. Usually 11 marginals lie on each side, and the undivided supracaudal scute is downturned between the somewhat expanded marginals. The carapace is yellowish brown or olive, with black blotches on the vertebrals and pleurals. The well-developed plastron has a deep anal notch. Its forelobe tapers anteriorly and is shorter and narrower than the hind lobe. The plastral formula is: abd> fem > pect ≥ hum > gul > an. The gulars are somewhat thickened, and the bridge is wide with small axillary and a larger inguinal scute. The plastron and bridge are yellow and usually unpatterned. The head is moderate with a non- protruding snout and a weakly hooked, tricuspid upper jaw. Its large prefrontal scale is longitudinally divided, and followed by a large frontal scale which is often subdivided; other head scales are small. The head is pale cream to yellowish green without dark spots or blotches. Limbs are brown to olive. The anterior surface of the forelimb is covered with moderate to small overlapping scales (the outermost largest). Males have longer, thicker tails, and deeper anal notches than do females. (Ernst & Barbour 1989)Manouria emys	Description (genus): The Asian tortoises of this genus lack hinges on either the carapace or plastron. The oval carapace may be either domed or flattened dorsally, and may have or lack a cervical indentation. Both the anterior and posterior marginals may be serrated. Usually 11 marginals lie on each side, and the supracaudal is divided into two scutes. The cervical scute is broad and triangular, and no submarginal scutes are present. Neurals are hexagonal, and there are usually two suprapygals. The plastron is well developed and has a deep anal notch. The entoplastron lies anterior to the humero-pectoral seam. Axillary and inguinal buttresses are short, and barely touch the costals. The skull is moderate to long with only a slightly hooked upper jaw. The triturating surface of the maxilla is strongly ridged, but the premaxilla lacks a ridge. The maxillae do not contribute to the roof of the palate, and the anterior orbito-nasal foramina are small, but the lateral caroticum foramen, containing the palatine artery, is large. The prootic bone is well exposed dorsally and anteriorly, and the quadrate bone usually encloses the stapes. There is no supraangular process. Limbs are club shaped with five claws on each forefoot. The two living species are the least derived of extant tortoises, sharing primitive mental glands with batagurines (Winokur and Legler, 1975). (Ernst & Barbour 1989)Key to the species of Manouria: Ernst & Barbour 1989: 241Recognition: This tortoise is the largest in Asia. Its oval carapace (to 60 cm) is domed with descending sides; however, it may be somewhat flattened across the 2d and 3d vertebrals. There is little indentation in the cervical region; instead both the anterior and posterior marginals are upturned and slightly serrated. A rather broad cervical scute is present. Vertebrals are wider than long; the 5th is expanded. Well-defined growth annuli surround the flat areolae of the vertebrals and pleurals. Eleven marginals lie on each side, and the supracaudals are divided both dorsally and ventrally. The carapace varies from olive or brown to black; vertebral and pleural areolae may be tan in young individuals. The plastron is well developed and has both an anterior and a posterior notch. Plastral lobes are almost equal in length and width. The plastral formula is: abd> hum > gul >< fem > an > pect; the pectoral scutes may or may not extend to the midseam. The gulars are thickened and extend beyond the carapacial rim. The bridge is wide; the two or more inguinal scales are larger than the single axillary. The plastron is yellow with black shading, usually around the periphery. The head is moderate to large with a nonprojecting snout and a slightly hooked upper jaw. Its prefrontal is divided longitudinally, and followed by a single large frontal scale; other head scales are small. The head is black with some pink, bronze, or brown pigment. Limbs and tail are black. The anterior surface of each forelimb is covered with large, pointed, overlapping scales. Several very large pointed tubercles (spurs) occur on each thigh, giving rise to the colloquial name of "six-footed" tortoise. The tail ends in a horny scale. Males have longer, thicker tails and more concave plastra than females. (Ernst & Barbour 1989)Geographic Variation: Manouria emys emys (Schlegel and Müller, 1844) ranges from southern Thailand (Ranong, Nakorn, and Si Thammaraj provinces) through Malaysia to Sumatra, Borneo, and some of the smaller islands of the Indo-Australian Archipelago. It has a flattened brown carapace (to 48 cm), with lighter vertebral and pleural areolae; the pec™ torals are widely separated. M. e. phayrei (Blyth, 1853) occurs in Assam, Burma, and from Tak Province in northern Thailand to Kanchanaburi Province in the central region. It is almost totally black with a domed, not conspicuously flattened, carapace which may reach 60 cm, and its pectorals meet at the midline of the plastron. Wirot (1979) was apparently unaware of Blyth's earlier description and attributed the name Geochelone nutapundi Reimann to this race. (Ernst & Barbour 1989)Psammobates geometricus	Description: “A small tortoise with a high, domed carapace that lacks a hinge. A nuchal is present. The paired gulars are longer than they are broad. There are 11-12 marginals (numbers 4-7 being higher than they are broad) that are sli<rhtly upturned at the back. The scutes are only slightly raised. There is a single axillary scale. The beak is hooked. The forelimbs each have five claws and are covered with scattered, large scales that are separated by smaller ones. Buttock tubercles are absent. The tail does not have a terminal spine. The carapace is beautifully marked with geometric patterns; the scutes have yellow centres from which yellow rays (8-15 on the vertebrals, 9-12 on the costals and 2-4 on the marginals) radiate, separated by black. The plastron is yellow, with radiating faint black rays and bands. Many juveniles have a single yellow 'X' on each carapace scute and a black plastron; the radial pattern develops with age. Females are more common than males.” (Branch 1998: 32)Size: TL 80-120 mm; max. TL 143 mm female, 123 mm male. Females are slightly larger (males average 106 mm and 207 g; females average 125 mm and 436 g). (Branch 1998: 32)Kinixys nogueyi	Description: “K. b. nogueyi (Lataste, 1886) occurs in West Africa from Senegal eastward to Cameroon and the Central African Republic. This subspecies has only four claws on each forefoot, the pectoral midseam 28-39% of the length of the combined gular and humeral midseams and 22-36% of the abdominal midseam, and a domed carapace (length/height ratio < 2.3) which is uniformly brown or with yellow areolae bordered with dark pigment.” (Ernst & Barbour 1989: 230)Psammobates oculifer	Description: “Similar to G. pardalis, but has a nuchal shield. Marginals flared, often quite markedly. The beak is hooked and tricuspid, and the jaw surfaces more or less serrated. Frontal and prefrontal scales fragmented. The unequal tubercular scales on the front face of the forelimb include a single conspicuously enlarged scute. At least one enlarged sub-conical tubercle on each thigh, often surrounded by smaller subsidiary tubercles. The patterns on the carapace may be very attractive, and the shells of this species are often used as decorative containers. The plastron is yellowish with light to dark brown markings; the vertebrals and laterals are marked with light stars formed by stripes on the laminae radiating out from the areolae towards the margin which vary considerably in number, about 6-12 per scute. The general shade of the shell may have an olive or grey tinge.” (Auerbach 1987: 68)Size: Length of shell 120-150 mm in adults (Auerbach 1987: 68).Kinixys belliana	Description: “This distinctive species is easy to identify. The hinge in adults is the salient feature, though in juveniles the costal scutes (see Genus Kinixys above) should be examined. Postorbital bar in·skull very thin or entirely absent. The carapace is neither spinose nor serrated. The posterior slope is from the middle of the 5th vertebral. 5-9 scutes on the fore-limb from the elbow to the outer claw. The shape of the shell in lateral profile is hump-backed, with the posterior part of the carapace falling away sharply. Colour varies considerably. The carapace pattern and colour are highly variable, but often radiate (in the eastern Hardveld specimens of plain straw yellow with dark flecks only are common). Juveniles are often marked with attractive radiating patterns, but a variety is found, and adults fade to straw yellow to light brown with varying darker marks.(Auerbach 1987: 69; this description may refer to spekii)Size: Up to 200 mm (Auerbach 1987: 69)Astrochelys radiata	Description: “This is the largest of the star tortoises, with a maximum weight of 22 kg. In contrast to G. elegans, which lives in India and which it closely resembles, A. radiata has a nuchal scute, and the carapace is evenly rounded, with vertical marginals on the sides, whereas the Indian species has somewhat conical scutes and, when very young, denticulate marginal scutes. Furthermore, the forelimbs of the radiated tortoise are quite distinctive, adapted for the sandy terrain where it lives. The forelimbs are large and covered with fine skin and small rounded scales, with a rounded tip, like a slipper. The elbow is very mobile, and it makes possible wide sweeps with the forelimbs similar to the strokes made by sea turtles. The head is bicolored-brown-black on top and yellow below a line that originates at the back of the eye. The overall coloration is blackish, with numerous brilliant yellow rays that emerge, fanlike, from the areola on one-third or one-half of the surface of the scute. Old animals may lose their markings and become almost unicolored, with tones ranging from brown to beige. Males are a little smaller than females (15 kg maximum) and often have a very concave plastron and thickened xiphiplastral area. The penis is half the length of the carapace and is often extended after rain, when the animal is excited and gets up on its legs to seek a partner. The penis has an arrowhead-shaped extremity, designed to locate and penetrate the cloaca of the female. The young are like living jewels, with no two having identical designs. [...] The decor may range from yellow or cream marked with black to black marked with yellow, with a great variety of markings, dark or light rays, and an overall color ranging from whitish to orange.” (Bonin 2006)Chersina angulata	Description: A medium-sized tortoise that grows larger in the western regions. In the east males rarely exceed 220 mm (1 kg), while on Dassen Island and the adjacent west coast mainland even females may exceed 240 mm (1.5 kg). The carapace is never hinged; it is elongate and flared at the front and behind in mature males. The scutes are slightly raised. There are 10-12 (usually 11) marginals. A nuchal is present. The gular is single and protrudes beneath the head in mature males. The beak is weakly hooked, bi- or tricuspid, and is rarely serrated. There are five claws on each of the forefeet. Buttock tubercles are absent. The tail does not have a terminal spine. The carapace is light straw-yellow in colour. The top scutes have dark brown areolae and black edges. The marginals have a black triangle on the posterior edges. The plastron has a dark, irregular centre, often with white sutures in old animals, and the abdominals are light orange to bright red (particularly in W. Cape 'rooipens' form). Old adults become smoothshelled and a uniform dirty straw colour. Unlike most other tortoises, males grow larger than females; the males have a 'peanut' shape, an elongate gular and deep concavity in the plastron. (Branch 1998: 30)Size: TL 150-250 mm; max. TL 300 mill, male. (Branch 1998: 30)Kinixys spekii	Description: A medium-sized tortoise with a smooth, depressed carapace with a well-developed hinge. The beak is unicuspid, and the supracaudal undivided with a smooth underside. Mature males have a concave plastron. The shell of juveniles has a zonary pattern, each shield having a dark brown centre with concentric light and dark zones. These may persist in males (which may also be uniform olive-brown to buff), whilst the dark zones break up into ragged rays in adult females. The belly is a uniform dirty yellow in males, with vague zonary patterning in females and juveniles. (Branch 1998: 34)Size: TL 140-160 mm; max. TL 183 mm. (Branch 1998: 34)Psammobates tentorius	Description: A small tortoise that comes in a bewildering range of shapes and colours. This single species has at times been divided into no fewer than six species with 22 races. The carapace is domed or flat, with or without raised scutes, and is not hinged. A nuchal is present, typically broader than it is long, and is often minute but rarely absent. The paired gulars are longer than they are broad. There are usually 11 (sometimes 10 or 12) marginals (numbers 4-7 being broader than they are high). Two to three (rarely one) axillaries are present. The beak is usually hooked and bi- or tricuspid. The forelimbs each have five claws and are covered with large, abutting scales. Buttock tubercles are typically present, but may be reduced or absent in the western race. The tail does not have a terminal spine. Coloration is varied; the carapace usually has geometric patterning (see Subspecies). The males have longer tails and a shallow plastral concavity.” (Branch 1998: 32)Size: TL 80-120 mm; max. TL 150 mm, female. The males are much smaller than the females, rarely exceeding 100 mm (Branch 1998: 32)Subspecies: P. t. tentorius is a large race. Its carapace scutes are strongly raised into knobs, with a well-marked pattern of yellow to orange radiating stripes on a black background. The plastron has solid mahogany markings in the centre and a yellow to orange edge. It occurs in SE Cape, from Grahamstown to Matjiesfontein, intergrading with the next race in central Karoo. P. t. verroxii has a carapace with smooth or faintly raised scutes, and is a drab colour, sometimes uniform brown, but usually with dull orange stripes on a dark brown background. The plastron has diffuse or indistinct dark brown patterning. It occurs in N. and central Karoo, intergrading with the next race in Bushmanland and S. Namibia. P.t. trimeni is the most attractive and smallest race, its carapace having small knobs and being well-marked with rich orange-yellow stripes (shading to red around the marginals) on a black background. The dark brown centre of the plastron is broken by lighter patches. It occurs in Namaqualand and S. Namibia, intergrading with the previous race in the east. (Branch 1998: 33)Homopus femoralis	Description: A small tortoise that weighs only 200-300 g, but is, nonetheless, the largest padloper. It lacks a hinge, but has a nuchal and paired gulars, and usually 11 marginals. The beak is not hooked, is tricuspid, and has a serrated edge. The nostrils are below the level of the eye. The forelimbs are covered with large, overlapping scales and have four claws. Buttock tubercles are present, but may be small or absent in juveniles. The tail does not have a terminal spine. The carapace is olive or reddish-brown; the individual scutes of juveniles often having black margins. The plastron is uniform dirty yellow-green in adults, often with darker areas restricted to the anterior edge of the scutes in juveniles. The skin of the body is yellow-brown, and sometimes orange-pink. Males do not have concave plastrons, but have longer tails. Females grow larger than males. (Branch 1998: 26) Size: TL 100-130 mm; max. TL 168 mm, female (Branch 1998: 26) Kinixys natalensis	Description: A small tortoise with a slightly convex carapace and a poorly-developed hinge. A nuchal is present. Combined, the gulars are more than twice as wide as they are long. There are 12-13 marginals on each side; they are not serrated or upturned. The supracaudal is usually divided. There are 2-3 axillaries. The beak is tricuspid. The forefeet each have five claws and are covered with large, overlapping, sometimes pointed scales. Buttock tubercles are absent. The tail has a terminal spine which is large in males. The carapace shield displays concentric patterning, with the areolae light to dark brown with concentric rings of orange-yellow and black-brown; there is a similar ringed pattern on the plastron shield that may fade in adults. Males lack a concave plastron and are smaller than females. (Branch 1998: 35)Size: TL 80-120 mm; max. TL 155 mm. (Branch 1998: 35)Kinixys lobatsiana	Description: Medium-sized with a smooth, moderately convex to depressed carapace with a well-developed hinge. The beak is unicuspid. The supracaudal is undivided, with a longitudinal groove on the underside. The posterior marginals are serrated and curve upwards. Mature males have a concave plastron. Juveniles and females have a broken radiate pattern on each carapace shield, and each shield has a red-brown centre. Males are usually uniform brown. The plastron is uniform dirty yellow in adult males, but with sparce, dark, radiating streaks in females and juveniles. (Branch 1998: 35)Size: TL 150-180 mill; max. TL 200 mm, female. (Branch 1998: 35)Pyxis planicauda	Description. “The wide tail of the male, which is rather flattened in a horizontal plane is not apparent in the females. On the other hand, the common name refers to the "flat back." This is the more elongated of the two species of Pyxis, and the shell is often flattened at the level of the second to fourth vertebral scutes. In general the coloration resembles that of P. arachnoides, and the similarity is enhanced by the spiderlike designs; the background is cream to beige, with radiating, geometric, dark brown to black designs on each of the scutes. The contrast, very marked in the hatchlings, is reduced with age, and very old animals may be quite plain. This species differs from P. arachnoides in the following characters: no plastral hinge; flat tail in males; carapace more elongate, flatter on top, with individual scutes also rather flat, giving the animal the shape of a loaf of bread; gular area extended and bilobed; marginals serrated toward the middle of the series and forming a rounded surface where they connect to the bridges; front and rear marginals strongly serrated; head dark, usually greenish brown, with less contrast than in P. arachnoides. The carapace length reaches 160 mm. In this species, the space between the plastron and the carapace, at the level of the tail, is extremely narrow so that the area between the abdominal and femoral scutes needs to open before actual oviposition, and the hind lobe of the plastron itself also become more flexible, thus providing space for the egg to pass.” (modified after Bonin 2006)Indotestudo travancorica	Description. “This species is slightly smaller than a I. elongata, with a maximum length of 300 mm in the males. It often has a depression at the rear of the shell, of the fourth vertebral scute or between the fourth and the fifth. A conical spur iS present at the end of the tail. The species is differentiated from the other two Indotestudo species by the following features: there is never a nuchal scute; the ratio between the interhumeral and the interpectoral seams averages 1.22 (i.e., it lies between the values for l. elongata and I. forstenii). The color ranges from chocolate to red-brown, with fairly large but diffuse and poorly contrasting black markings. The plastron may be immaculate (i.e., overall red-brown), or there may be diffuse black markings on each scute. The color of the head is similar to that of its congeners — creamy white, becoming reddish during the mating season. (Bonin 2006)Astrochelys yniphora	Description. “This turtle measures up to 400 mm in length and reaches a maximum weight of 8 kg. The general form is similar to that of A. radiata, but it differs in the following points: the gular is very extended, in the form of a plowshare, and its coloration is not radiating but tends toward plain yellow. The elongated gular is rather thin and upcurved, is unique among chelonians, and permits the males to challenge each other vigorously during the breeding season. In the female, the gular is much smaller. During the early years of life, this tortoise is yellow and black, with wide, very dark seams, well marked growth rings, and sometimes quadrangular markings on the scutes. Later this pattern evolves into a uniform cream or whitish. The plastron is yellowish, and the sutures are brown. There is very little plastral concavity in the males. The head is beige-yellow to brown and has well-demarcated scales and a more "smiling" physiognomy than its southern cousin, A. radiata. The limbs are covered with wide, well-developed scales. [...] The hatchlings weigh about 25 g. They are yellowish with large brown markings on each scute.” (Bonin 2006)Chelonoidis niger	Diagnosis (chathamensis). No nuchal; gulars paired; fourth cervical vertebra biconvex; carapace depressed, front elevated in male; height at nuchal notch less than 41% of straight length (male 34, female 27%); male flat-backed, female dome-shaped, differcnce between percentages of heights at third vertebral and at nuchal notch 6 in male. 24 in femalc; carapace of male slightly saddle-shaped but broad, width at margin of junction of second and third marginals 53% in male; antcrior marginals but little everted; length over curve in male 112%, female 126%; vertical distance from lower surface of plastron to lower edge of lateral marginals smalI, 4% in male, 6% in female; general size moderate, straight length in male 35.25 inches, female 22.5 inches; pectoral plates much reduced, not meeting on mid-line; jaws and throat of female black (Van Denburgh 1907: 4).Diagnosis (darwini). No nuchal; gulars paired; fourth cervical vertebra biconvex; carapace high, elongate, somewhat dome-shaped but high in iront; posterior declivity beginning about middle of third verte- bral; height at nuchal notch more than 41% (45%) of straight length; difference bctween percentages of height at third vertebral and at nuchal notch more than 9 (10); carapace not saddle-shaped, width at margin cf junction of second and third marginals 55%; width over curve in male not greater than length over curve; vertical distance from lower surface of plastron to tower edge of lateral marginals moderately great (9%); general size large, straight length 38 inches; shell heavy; pectoral plates forming a suture on median line; the sum of the measurements of the length over curve, length of plastron, height at nuchal notch, and height at third vertebral, equals or exceeds the sum of the measurements of the straight length, straight width, and width over curve; jaws and throat black (Van Denburgh 1907: 4).Diagnosis (donfaustoi). “The new species can be diagnosed by a combination of genetic, morphological, and geographic distribution evidence.” (POULAKAKIS et al. 2015).There are no diagnostic morphological characters that uniquely define the new species. However, “linear and geometric morphometric analyses reveal consistent differences in mean shell size and shape between tortoises from Reserva and Cerro Fatal. Tortoises from Reserva are larger in size and have a relatively larger carapace with higher anterior opening than the Cerro Fatal tortoises” (POULAKAKIS et al. 2015).Diagnosis (hoodensis). No nuchaI; gu!ars paired; front of carapace high, Iittle lower than middle, height at nuchal notch more than 41% (45%) of straight length; difference between percentages of heights at third vertebral and at nuchal notch less than 9 (5); carapace saddle-shaped, narrow anteriorly. width at margin of junction of second and third marginals not more than 54% (45%); first marginals not greatly enlarged, not much everted, their ventral surfaces not vertical, their most prominent points separated by less than 30% (20%); length over curve not more than 123% (122%) , greater than width over curve; vertical distance from lower surface of plastron to lower edge of lateral marginals great, 12%; general size rather smalI, straight length (June, 1907) 22.2 inches; plastron long, median length 89%; plates striated, central portions of vertebrals and costals much elevated; pectoral plates forming a suture on median line; tower jaw and throat marked with yellow (Van Denburgh 1907: 3).Diagnosis (phantasticus). No nuchal; gulars paired; fourth cervical vertebra biconvex; front of carapace high, not lower than middle, height at nuchal notch more than 41% (54%) of straight length; difference between percentages of height at third vertebral and at nuchal notch less than 9 (2); carapace saddle-shaped, narrow anteriorly. width at margin of junction of second and third marginals not more than 54% (46%); first marginals much enlarged, everted more than in any other race, their ventral surfaces nearly vertical, their edges from nuchal notch to prominent point nearly horizontal, prominent point almost a right angle; distance between prominent points of first marginals more than 30% (32%); length over curve more than 123 % (124 % ), greater than width over curvc; vertical di s tance from lower surface of plastron to lower edge of lateral marginaIs small, 6%; general size moderate, straight length 34.5 inches; plastron short, 70 %; pectoral plates forming a suture on median line; lower jaw and throat marked with yellow (Van Denburgh 1907: 4).Descriptions (subspecies): Ernst & Barbour 1989Homopus areolatus	Diagnosis (genus Homopus) (from Branch 2007): small African tortoises with the triturating surfaces of maxilla and premaxilla without ridges; maxillary not entering roof of palate; prootic narrowly exposed dorsally; quadrate enclosing  stapes; centrum of third cervical biconvex; carapace without hinge; no submarginal scutes; gulars divided; and gular region only slightly thickened (Auffenberg 1974).In addition to these features, the Aus tortoise (Homopus solus) possesses the following suite of characters that confirm its generic assignment to Homopus, and distinguish it from other tortoises in southern Africa: carapace depressed, with a distinct nuchal (c.f. Stigmochelys), paired gulars (c.f. Chersina) that are broader than long (c.f. Psammobates), and without a carapace hinge (c.f. Kinixys).Chersobius signatus	Diagnosis (genus): All Chersobius species have a single, large inguinal scute, whereas the number is variable in Homopus. The midline pectoral scute of Chersobius is consistently longer, and the nuchal scute shorter, than in Homopus. The fourth to fifth vertebral suture is narrow in Homopus and broad in Chersobius. Forelimb scales also differ with 3–4 large rows and 5–6 smaller rows, respectively, in Homopus and Chersobius. Chersobius males have a plastral concavity and Homopus males not. Two Chersobius species (C. signatus and C. boulengeri) are distinguishable from Homopus by having 12 or more marginal scutes, whereas Homopus species have 11 or fewer. The glans penes are respectively V-shaped and heart-shaped in Homopus and Chersobius. Ecological differences include that Chersobius species are rupicolous and inhabit arid regions, whereas Homopus species inhabit more mesic habitats. Homopus females produce multi-egg clutches and tend to be bigger compared to single-egg clutching Chersobius females. Females of all species are larger than conspecific males, and all males have larger shell openings than females have (Hofmeyr & Branch 2018).Diagnosis: “Posterior margin of carapace serrated a very large conical tubercle on thigh ; forehead covered with numerous small and irregular shields ; shell yellow, shaded with brown on the plastron, elegantly freckled and radiated with blackish brown on the carapace; length, 10 cm.” (Duerden 1906)Chersobius solus	Diagnosis: A small Homopus that forms part of the ‘Chersobius group’, and thus differs from H. areolatus and H. femoralis by possessing five claws on each forelimb, an obvious plastral concavity in mature males, a single inguinal and 11-12 marginals. Among the ‘Chersobius group’ it differs from H. signatus, its nearest geographical neighbour, and from H. boulengeri, to which it was originally referred (Mertens 1955, 1971), by having an areolar carapace colour pattern (usually speckled in signatus and patternless in boulengeri); usually lacking prominent buttock tubercles in both sexes (present in both sexes in signatus, but usually only in males in boulengeri); having two axillaries (usually single in both signatus and boulengeri); a tricuspid beak (usually bicuspid in signatus and rounded in boulengeri); a small, narrow nuchal (broad in signatus); a relatively shallower shell; fragmented prefrontals (usually more elongate and longitudinally divided in signatus and boulengeri); usually having 11 marginals (mainly 12 in signatusand always 12 or more in boulengeri); having a well-defined ridge on the bridge (rounded in boulengeri); and having the anal midline suture longer than the femoral (femoral suture longer than the anal in H. boulengeri).Gopherus morafkai	Diagnosis: All of the species of Gopherus and their hybrids can be easily diagnosed using molecular data. Morphologically, G. morafkai can be separated from both G. flavomarginatus and G. polyphemus in having relatively smaller front feet. Whereas the distance from the bases of the first to fourth claws is the same on all feet in G. morafkai, in the latter two species the distance from the bases of the first and third claws on the forelimb is about the same as the distance between the bases of the first and fourth claws on the hindlimb (Auffenberg and Franz 1978). The diagnosis of living specimens of G. morafkai, G. berlandieri and G. agassizii can be impossible in captive tortoises because of extensive hybridization (Edwards et al. 2010) and because of abnormalities in shell, head and limb integument from poor nutrition (Donoghue 2006). However, in non‐hybrid individuals, G. morafkai can be separated from G. berlandieri in having a rounded snout when viewed from above as opposed to a wedge‐shaped snout in G. berlandieri (Auffenberg and Franz 1978). Further, in G. morafkai the gular projections do not normally diverge, and it has a single axillary scale preceding each bridge, yet in G. berlandieri the gular projections often diverge and the axillary scales are often paired. Morphologically, G. morafkai can be separated from G. agassizii in having a relatively narrower shell, shorter gular scutes, shorter projections of the anal scutes and in having a flatter, pear‐shaped carapace (Table 1). Ecologically, whereas G. agassizii predominantly occurs in valleys and alluvial fan topography, G. morafkai prefers slopes and rocky hillsides (Riedle et al. 2008), including animals of the isolated population in northwestern Arizona (McLuckie et al. 1999).Gopherus evgoodei	Diagnosis: Molecular data can readily diagnose all species of Gopherus and their hybrids (Murphy et al. 2011; Edwards et al. 2016). Morphologically, G. evgoodei, G. agassizii and G. morafkai (the agassizii group) can be separated generally from both G. flavomarginatus Legler and G. polyphemus (Daudin) in having relatively smaller front feet. Whereas the distance from the bases of the first to fourth claws is the same on all feet in the agassizii group, in the latter two species the distance from the bases of the first and third claws on the forelimb is about the same as the distance between the bases of the first and fourth claws on the hindlimb (Auffenberg and Franz 1978). Living captive specimens of the agassizii group and G. berlandieri cannot all be dis- tinguished morphologically because of extensive hybridization (Edwards et al. 2010) and developmental abnormalities in shell, head and limb integument from poor nutri- tion (Donoghue 2006). However, in native non-hybrid individuals, G. berlandieri can be separated from the agassizii group in having a wedge-shaped snout when viewed from above in contrast to a rounded snout (Fig. 12) (Auffenberg and Franz 1978). Further, the gular projections of G. berlandieri often diverge in large males and the species often exhibits paired axillary scales preceding each bridge. In contrast, the gular projections do not normally diverge in the agassizii group and there is a single axillary scale. Morphological characters among the agassizii group exhibit overlap (Germano 1993; McLuckie et al. 1999) and characters like coloration in desert tortoises can be highly variable (Legler and Vogt 2013). However, G. evgoodei differs from G. morafkai and G. agassizii (Table 1). Gopherus evgoodei is flatter in shell profile (Fig. 2). It has rounded foot pads, multiple enlarged spurs on the radial-humeral joint (Fig. 3). The new species has short tails (Fig. 4), orange tones in the integument (skin) and shell (Fig. 5), and a distinctly shallower concavity on the plastron of males.Chersobius boulengeri	Original description: “Shell very depressed, more than twice as long as deep, flat on the vertebral region, posterior margin reverted, nearly vertical and not or feebly serrated, anterior margin not or feebly serrated; dorsal shields not swollen, concentrically striated, separated by rather deep, narrow grooves ; areole either moderately or deeply impressed vertebral shields broader than long, as broad or a little narrower than the costals a small, short nuchal, about as broad behind as long. Marginal plates 12 or 13, rarely 11. Plastral lobes short, from half to one-third the width of the bridge, front lobe truncate, hind lobe openly notched in the female, deeper in the male the longest median suture is between the abdominals, and is a little over three times that between the pectorals, the suture between the caudals is about the same as that between the pectorals and the gulars, the suture between the femoral is the same or a little shorter than that between the humerals : axillaries small, inguinals large, in contact with the femoral, the abdominal, and two marginals. A pair of small prefronta} scales on the snout, usually preceded by a small median and two lateral plates of nearly the same size as the prefrontale. Beak strongly hooked, feebly tridentate. Fore limbs covered anteriorly with large, elongated, subequal, imbricate scales or tubercles five claws to the fore limb, four rarely five, to the hind limb: a large conical tubercle on the hinder side of the thigh, surrounded with smaller tubercles in the male. (Duerden 1906)Colour: Carapace nearly uniformly dark reddish or yellowish brown in living specimens, yellowish in old dead shells, anterior three or four neural shields may be narrowly edged with black in front and on the sides: plastral shields uniformly dark olive or yellowish, often dark brown anteriorly; naked parts of skin bright yellow when alive, with minute orange scales. (Duerden 1906)Length: Largest shell 10.5 cm. (Duerden 1906)Kinixys zombensis	Original description: “This is founded on an adult female example from Zomba, Nyasaland, collected by Mr. L. Smith (24th Aug., 1906). Type in the Albany Museum collection. The shell is high and rounded, resembling the typical form, but stouter ; posteriorly it descends rather steeply, but anteriorly the upper surface passes down to the front margin of the carapace quite gradually and with low obliquity, without any abruptness in the region of the first vertebral. Shields not raised, passing insensibly into each other. Nuchal shield rather narrow. greatest width about 4*5 mm.; first vertebral shield 5-sided, with an acute angle anteriorly fourth vertebral broader than long (49 x 37 mm.), and posterior margin as broad as the anterior one; margin of carapace only slightly upturned posteriorly, most noticeably so on eleventh marginal, and to less extent on the posterior median shield; anal suture rather short, shorter than femoral (13 : 22) ; pectoral suture of moderate length (18), although rather shorter than femoral; gular shields together forming an exactly equilateral triangle, the base of which projects in front only slightly beyond the anterior angles of the humerals, the median notch slight. Front margin of carapace well-recurved in the middle. Lateral keels on marginals V-VII weak and smooth. The colour markings are conspicuously radial. The areolæ of the shields are yellowish at their margin, darker centrally vertebrals I -V have each 6 broad, black rays radiating from the areole, the median rays being broadest; costals also with 5 or 6 black rays each. Margins with black radial markings. Plastron yellow with some black markings on all the shields: those on the abdominal shields are pronouncedly radial, although no long rays occur, the large central areols being yellow. Central parts of plastron yellow.” (Hewitt 1931)MEASUREMENTS. “Length of plastron 154, of carapace 172 ; breadth of carapace 113, height of shell 80 mm. These figures, compared with those given by Schmidt for Congo specimens of belliana, show that the breadth of the carapace compared with the length of the plastron is decidedly greater in zombensis.” (Hewitt 1931) Variation: “Of this sub-species the British Museum possesses a series of large specimens from Beira. The gular shields have much the same shape throughout as in the type. The anals, on the other hand, are variable in form, being either very long, or short and broad. One large specimen has no nuchal. Most of them have no raised shields on the carapace, but in one old and abnormal specimen the last vertebral is slightly so. The inguinal shield is. either in broad or narrow contact with marginal VI, or may be just separated therefrom in older specimens, which show thickening of the plastron in these latter, marginal VI has an acute-angled anterior projection. In a single juvenile example the anals are rather short, and inguinal is just in contact with marginal VI.” (Hewitt 1931)Original description (zuluensis): “The Natal Museum has a large male example (fig. 2, type) from. the sand-dunes of Richards Bay, Zululand (coll. Mr. G. Rump). This has conspicuous radial markings on the neural and costal' shields. The black radii are nowhere so broad as in zombensis, but on the fourth vertebral are nevertheless all broader than the pale interspaces : in many places they tend to break up into much narrower radial streaks. On the plastron black markings. are obsolete, and on the marginals they are broken up and indefinite. Neural and costal shields separated by deep grooves. and sometimes more or less raised ; vertebral V Is most strongly raised. A long and narrow nuchal. Anal shields not very short, the suture subequal to that of the femoral. Pectoral' suture moderately long, nearly half as long as abdominal (25 : 54), longer than the femoral, but shorter than humeral. Gulars. subtriangular, broader than long (36 27), notched and deeply grooved in front; in front they project somewhat. Anterior lobe of plastron narrow, the sides only slightly curved. Inguinal in contact with marginal VI or VII.” (Hewitt 1931)MEASUREMENTS (zuluensis). Length of plastron 182, breadth of carapace 132, height of carapace 94 ; fourth vertebral in front 35, behind 30 mm. (Hewitt 1931) Variation (zuluensis): The Natal Museum has another large example (plastron 172* mm.) (Pl. XXXVIII, fig. 1) from Zululand which somewhat. resembles the type of zombensis, but differs in possessing a' distinct hump in the region of the first vertebral; and at this. point the carapace is slightly higher than posteriorly. Carapace. only slightly depressed; vertebral IV distinctly broader than long, but narrower behind than in front; hind margin of carapace nowhere upturned; marginals V-VII with well-smoothed nearly obsolete lateral keels. Pectoral suture long, almost as long as the femoral; anal suture very short, gulars triangular, the base much longer than the sides (33•5 : 28). Plastron with pronounced radial markings on the abdominal shields, the black radii being numerous, long and slender. Another smaller specimen (plastron 145 mm.) in the Albany Museum, of uncertain origin, but suspected to be from Zululand, has the following characters : the carapace shields are not raised, nor separated by deep grooves; the conspicuous radial pattern is like that of zombensis, but the lateral black rays of the neural shields are narrower, and the abdominal shields have a number of long black ravs. The pectoral suture is longer than in zombensis, being only a little shorter than the humeral, the gulars are broader in front, and the fourth vertebral is narrower behind. The hind margin of the carapace is not in the least upturned. The Transvaal Museum has two remarkable specimens (Pl. XXXVIII, figs. 8-10) from Matubatuba, Zululand, collected by Mr. H. Bell-Marley; the locality is a few miles inland from St. Lucia Bay and just north of the Umfolosi River. The female has the following characters: Gular shields together form a nearly equilateral triangle, base scarcely projecting in front, and a little longer than the side; lateral margin of pectoral shield arched, and presenting a slight salient in the middle: pectoral suture rather long, being almost half the abdominal anterior and posterior lobes of plastron both broad and short anal suture a little shorter than femoral; inguinal shield with acute anterior angle, meeting marginal VI; marginals V-VII with lateral keels, but they are not sharp; hinder marginals not upturned ; carapace well-arched, highest behind, with conspicuous radial markings, but the black rays are much reduced in number, each shield being pale horn colour with only a few quite narrow, long, black rays, but no broad ones, and areole not infuscated; plastron pale, with very little infuscation, several long, thin black rays being present on the abdominals. The carapace is relatively broader than the type of zombensis, and the vertebral and costal shields do not pass insensibly into each other, but tend to be slightly raised. No well-marked angle in the region of vertebral I, although that shield is slightly raised. Vertebral IV considerably narrower behind.” (Hewitt 1931)MEASUREMENTS (zuluensis). Length of plastron 157, breadth of carapace 124, height of carapace 83, anal suture 15, femoral suture 18, pectoral suture 24-5, humeral suture 26, gular suture 20 mm.Variation (zuluensis): The male is abnormal, having extensive thickening of the bony plates and the horny shields of the carapace are altogether altered through fusion and exfoliation. In the plastron, also greatly thickened, the gulars project somewhat, but the outline remains nearly equilateral and the front margin is only faintly notched; anal suture short; inguinals pointed in front; lateral margin of humeral shield straight, not arched, the anterior lobe of the plastron being much narrower than in female; ventral borders of all the hinder marginals much thickened and rounded. Plastron quite without dark rays. Pectoral suture shorter than femoral or humeral (17, 20-5, 33 mm.). In general form the female from Matubatuba resembles somewhat that from Naauwpoort referred to lobatsiana, but is larger. There are, however, striking differences in the ornamentation, and the gular and anal shields are more projecting in lobatsiana.” (Hewitt 1931)Aldabrachelys gigantea	Recognition: Among the tortoises, this species is second only in size to the slightly larger species found in the Galapagos Islands. G. gigantea reaches a record carapace length of 105 cm and may weigh 120 kg. It has a thick, elongated, domed carapace with descending sides, only a slight cervical indentation at best, and posterior marginals that are flared, slightly upturned, and unserrated. A cervical scute is usually present. Vertebrals are broader than long, the 5th is smallest and expanded, and the 1st is narrower than the 2d. Growth annuli surround the raised vertebral and pleural areolae, but these are generally low, and the carapace may be worn very smooth in old individuals. Usually 11 marginals lie on each side of the carapace, and the supracaudal is single, undivided, and downturned between the posterior marginals. The carapace is uniformly brownish gray. In comparison to other tortoises, the plastron is somewhat a short and lacks a posterior notch. Its forelobe tapers anteriorly and is longer, but much narrower, than the hind lobe. The plastral formula is: abd > hum > fem > pect >< gul >< an; the paired gulars are short and thick and scarcely project beyond the carapacial rim. The bridge is moderate in width (about one-third the carapace length), and bears a single small axillary scute and a larger inguinal. The plastron and bridge are also brownish gray. The head is narrowly pointed and somewhat wedge shaped (when compared to Galapagos tortoises), and with a convex forehead. The snout is nonprojecting, and the upper jaw is either weakly hooked or bi- or tricuspid. The large prefrontal scale is divided longitudinally, its sides are parallel and do not diverge posteriorly; a relatively small frontal scale follows, and other head scales are small. Head, neck, limbs, and tail are gray. The anterior surface of the forelimbs is covered with large, slightly rounded, nonoverlapping scales. No conical tubercles occur on the thighs, and the tail a lacks a large terminal scale. Males are larger and have longer, thicker tails than do the smaller females. (Ernst & Barbour 1989)Pyxis arachnoides	Recognition: The domed, hingeless carapace (to 15 cm) has descending, almost parallel sides, a notch in the cervical region, and unserrated, downturned posterior marginals. A cervical scute may be absent but, when present, is long and narrow. Vertebrals are broader than long with slightly raised centers surrounded by prominent growth annuli. Neurals alternate in shape between octagonal and square; two suprapygals are present. Eleven marginals lie on each side; the supracaudal is undivided. No submarginal scales are present. Each dark-brown or black vertebral and pleural contains a starlike pattern consisting of a yellow center from which extend several rather broad rays (usually 6-8 on each vertebral, 4-6 on each pleural). The plastron is well developed, and its forelobe is longer but narrower than the hind lobe, and tapered toward the front. A movable hinge lies between the humeral and pectoral scutes (between the epiplastra and hyoplastra, either crossing the posterior portion of the entoplastron or behind it) allowing the forelobe to be raised to almost close the anterior portion of the shell. The hind lobe is broad and very short with a posterior notch. The plastral formula is: abd > gul > pect > hum >< an > fem; the paired gulars are not greatly thickened, and only extend slightly past the carapacial rim when the forelobe is at its lowest position. A single small axillary and one or two larger inguinal scutes lie on the broad bridge. Axillary and inguinal buttresses are short and do not extend to the costals. The plastron varies from totally yellow to having some dark blotching at the bridge. Axillary and inguinal buttresses are short and do not extend to the costals. The plastron varies from totally yellow to having some dark blotching at the bridge. The head is moderate in size with a nonprotruding snout and a slightly hooked upper jaw. Its premaxillae and maxillae lack a median ridge and the sides of the jaws have serrations. The quadrate does not enclose the stapes and the anterior palatine foramina are large. The head is black with some yellow speckles. The neck is odd in having either totally procoelous cervical vertebrae or the second biconvex, only a rare anomaly in other turtles (Williams, 1950a). Limbs are clublike with five claws on each forefoot. On the anterior surface of the foreleg are seven or eight longitudinal rows of enlarged, nonoverlapping scales. Spurlike scales occur on the heel, and some blunt tubercles on the thighs. A longitudinal row of large nonoverlapping scales also lies on the anterior surface of the hind leg. The tail ends in a spinelike scale. Limbs and tail are yellowish brown. (Ernst & Barbour 1989)Geographic Variation: Three subspecies are currently recognized. Pyxis arachnoides arachnoides Bell, 1827 occurs along the southwestern coast of Madagascar in the vicinity of the Onilahy River, which virtually splits its range into northern and southern portions. Its uniformly yellow plastron has a movable hinge, forward projecting gulars, and axillary scutes only a little longer than broad when viewed from beneath. P. a. oblonga Gray, 1869a ranges along the southern coast of Madagascar from La Linta to Lake Anony. Its plastron has a movable anterior hinge, some black pigment or blotches, and only slightly projecting gulars. Its axillary scutes are broader than long when viewed from below. P. a. brygooi (Vuillemin and Domergue, 1972) occurs in the northern portion of the range, southwest of the Mangoky River between Morombe, Lake Ihotry, and Fanemotra Bay. It lacks mobility in its anterior plastral hinge, has some black pigment on the plastron, slightly projecting gulars, and axillary scutes longer than broad when viewed from beneath. (Ernst & Barbour 1989)Sexual dimorphism: Males have longer, thicker tails. (Ernst & Barbour 1989)Kinixys homeana	Recognition: The elongated carapace (to 21 cm) is domed with a flat, sometimes slightly keeled, dorsal surface, sloping sides, the anterior marginals flared but only slightly reverted, and the posterior marginals flared and strongly reverted and serrated. Only a shallow depression, at best, occurs in the cervical region, and the posterior portion of the carapace begins to drop off abruptly at the front of the 5th vertebral. An elongated cervical is usually present (rarely absent). Vertebrals 2-5 are broader than long; the flared 5th is widest. Vertebral 1 is broader than long in juveniles, but becomes progressively longer with age until it is longer than broad.. disrupted keel, in the form of low knoblike projection on each vertebral, may be present on younger individuals; this keel is usually lost with age. There are 11 or rarely 12 marginals on each side, and a single, usually undivided, reverted supracaudal scute. Carapacial color ranges from totally dark brown to tan, or there may be some yellow pigment on the vertebrals and pleurals, or dark borders on these scutes. The thickened, paired gulars project only slightly beyond the carapacial rim, and are widely notched. The short plastral hind lobe is shallowly notched posteriorly. There are two to four small axillary scutes and a large inguinal (in contact with the femoral) on each bridge. The plastral formula is: abd > hum > gul >< pect >< fem > an. The plastron is dark brown to tan with some yellow at the seams. The brown to yellow head is small to moderate with a nonprojecting snout and a hooked upper jaw. Its prefrontal are divided longitudinally and the large frontal scale may be subdivided. Other head scales are small and irregularly shaped. The forelimbs have on their anterior surfaces a few scattered, large overlapping scutes in five to eight longitudinal rows. The thigh lacks enlarged tubercles, but the heel may have a large spurlike scale. There are five claws on each forefoot. The limbs and tail are brown to yellow. The tail ends in a clawlike tubercle. Males have longer, thicker tails and concave plastra. (Ernst & Barbour 1989: 231)Testudo marginata	Recognition: The elongated carapace (to 30.5 cm) is domed and highest just behind the center with abruptly descending sides, a weak cervical notch, and the serrated posterior rim greatly flared. A narrow cervical scute is present. Vertebrals are wider than long; the 5th is expanded. Areolae of the vertebral and pleural scutes may be raised slightly and are surrounded by growth annuli. Eleven marginals lie on each side; the undivided supracaudal is very flared, as also are the posterior marginals. The carapace is black to dark brown with yellow vertebral and pleural areolae, and a yellow bar on each marginal. The plastron is well developed, and its forelobe upturned, tapered toward the front, and shorter and narrower than the hind lobe, which bears a posterior notch. The plastral formula is: abd > an > hum >< pect >< fem > gul; the paired gulars are thickened and may project slightly beyond the carapacial rim. A single axillary and one or two moderately sized inguinals which may touch the femoral scute occur on the broad bridge. Plastron and bridge are yellow, with some dusky pigment on the bridge and two rows of large black triangular blotches along the plastron. The head is of moderate size with a nonprotruding snout and a hooked upper jaw. Its large prefrontal and frontal scales may be longitudinally divided or subdivided; other head scales are small. The head is black, the chin yellow or gray, and the jaws black or brown. Limbs are brown to yellowish brown. Four or five longitudinal rows of large overlapping scales lie on the anterior surface of each foreleg; each forefoot has five claws. Spurlike scales lie on each heel, and weak tubercles may occur on the thighs. The tail may lack a terminal claw. (Ernst & Barbour 1989)Sexual dimorphism: Males have longer, thicker tails with the vent near the tip. (Ernst & Barbour 1989)Indotestudo forstenii	Recognition: The elongated carapace (to 30.9 cm) is domed, but flattened dorsally, with descending sides; a cervical notch is due to the absence of any cervical scute; the posterior marginals are serrated (more strongly so in juveniles). Vertebrals are broader than long, the 5th is expanded. Well-defined growth annuli surround the vertebral and pleural areolae. There are usually 11 marginals on each side, and the single supracaudal scute may be downturned between the somewhat expanded posterior marginals. The carapace is either unpatterned gray to brown, or yellow brown to brown or olive with dark blotches on each scute. The plastron is well developed. Its forelobe tapers anteriorly and is shorter and narrower than the hind lobe. The plastral formula is: abd> fem >< hum > gul > pect > an. The gulars are somewhat thickened. The bridge is wide, and the axillary and inguinal scutes are moderate in size. Plastron and bridge are yellowish to brown with small black blotches. The head is moderate in size with a nonprotruding snout and a weakly hooked, tricuspid upper jaw. Its large prefrontal is divided longitudinally, and the single frontal scale is almost as large; other head scales are small. The head is yellow with some brown or orange pigment. Neck, limbs, and tail are brownish gray to olive. The anterior surface of the forelimbs is covered with large, yellow, irregularly shaped, overlapping scales (the outermost largest). Males have longer, thicker tails with the vent nearer the tip than do females. (Ernst & Barbour 1989)Kinixys erosa	Recognition: The elongated carapace (to 32.3 cm) is domed with a flat, unkeeled dorsal surface, sloping sides, the anterior marginals flared and reverted, and the posterior marginals only slightly flared but strongly serrated and reverted. A shallow depression occurs in the cervical region, and the posterior portion of the carapace slopes to the rear, but does not drop off nearly as abruptly as in K. homeana, and the sloping begins at the middle of the 5th vertebral. A cervical scute is only rarely present. All vertebrals are broader than long; the 5th is flared and widest. There are 11 or sometimes 12 marginals on each side, and the Supracaudal is not divided. Carapacial color ranges from totally dark brown to dark brown with yellow to orange centers on all scutes. Occasionally a band of yellow occurs along the base of the pleurals. The thickened, paired gulars project anteriorly beyond the carapacial rim, especially in males, and are notched in front. The short plastral hind lobe may lack a posterior notch or be shallowly notched. There are three or four small axillary scutes and one large inguinal (in contact with the femoral) on each bridge. The plastral formula is: abd > hum >< gul >< pect > fem >< an. The plastron is dark brown to black with some yellow along the seams. The head is small to moderate with a nonprojecting snout and a hooked upper jaw. Its prefrontals are divided longitudinally, the large frontal may be subdivided, and the rest of the head scales are small and irregularly shaped. The head varies from brown to yellow, but usually has some yellow pigment. Each forelimb has on its anterior surface a few large, sometimes overlapping scales in four or five longitudinal rows. Each thigh lacks enlarged tubercles and the heel usually has no spurlike enlarged scales. Five claws are present on each forefoot. Limbs and tail are brown. The tail ends in a clawlike tubercle. Males have longer, thicker tails and more projecting gulars than do females, and concave plastra. (Ernst & Barbour 1989: 230)Malacochersus tornieri	Recognition: The keelless, hingeless carapace (to 17.7 cm) is extremely flattened (some individuals are even swaybacked) and has nearly parallel sides. Lateral marginals are sometimes slightly upturned; posterior marginals are usually smooth in larger adults but may be slightly serrated in juveniles. There are 11 or 12 marginals on each side, and two supracaudals are present. Submarginal scutes are absent. The cervical scute is long and narrow in adults, and the vertebrals are broader than long with the middle three smallest. The 1st vertebral may be slightly pointed anteriorly, and is the 5th is flared. There is usually an indentation in the cervical region and, posteriorly, only a single suprapygal bone is present. The most unique feature of the carapace is the retention of the juvenile fenestra (windowlike openings between the carapacial bones) into adulthood (see figure). This condition is found in the hatchling stage of all tortoises, but these openings, at least in the dermal shell, usually close by adulthood. Some resorption of the endochondral ribs occurs in Malacochersus, which also occurs in other tortoises, the costal and peripheral bones are thin, and the neural bones are also shortened and weakened. These adaptations allow much flexibility in the carapace and permit the pancake tortoise to crawl into narrow crevices or under rocks to avoid predators and the heat of the sun. Apart from the fenestration, Loveridge and Williams (1957) felt the shell to be emydinelike and rather primitive. The entire morphology and development of the shell in Malacochersus has been well studied by Procter (1922). The carapace is yellow to tan with light areolae on the vertebrals and pleurals, and darker scute borders. Width of these dark scute borders is extremely variable, even within a single clutch, no two individuals look alike, and many have radiating yellow stripes crossing the dark borders. These variable patterns tend to camouflage the turtle in its natural dry habitat. The hingeless plastron is also persistently fenestrated (see figure). Its forelobe is only slightly anteriorly projecting, and the paired gular scutes are much broader than long, giving the appearance of lying transversely rather than longitudinally. There is a slight anterior notch between the gulars, and occasional individuals may also have an additional intergular scute. The hind lobe is posteriorly notched. Two, (rarely three) small axillary scutes and two to four inguinals are present on the bridge. The plastral formula is: abd > hum > pect >< fem > gul > an. The plastron is yellow with solid brown blotches or jagged brown radiations. The yellow-brown head is moderate in size with a nonprotruding snout and a hooked upper jaw which may be bior tricuspid. The premaxillae are ridgeless, but the triturating surfaces of the maxillae contain strong ridges. The edges of the jaws are slightly serrated. The prootic is well exposed dorsally and the quadrate encloses the stapes. The supranasal scales are large and usually in contact. There are also a single or double prefrontal scale and a large, sometimes subdivided, frontal scale. The other head scales are small. Limbs and tail are yellow brown. The toes lack webs but bear strong digging claws. The anterior surface of the forelimb is covered with large overlapping scales.  (Ernst & Barbour 1989: 275)Sexual dimorphism: Males have longer, thicker tails than do the slightly larger females. (Ernst & Barbour 1989: 275)Manouria impressa	Recognition: The oval carapace (to 27 cm) is flattened dorsally, has an indentation at the broad cervical, and is strongly serrated around its entire rim. Posterior marginals are somewhat upturned, and pleurals somewhat concave. Vertebrals are wider than long, and the 5th is expanded. Günther (1882) reported a slight indication of a medial keel on the 4th and/or 5th vertebrals. Well-defined growth annuli surround the flat vertebral and marginal areolae. Eleven marginals lie on each side, and two supracaudals. The carapace is yellowish brown to brown with dark seams, but some have dark radiations along the outer border of each scute. Large black blotches occur on the marginals. The plastron is well developed with a deep anal notch and a broad anterior notch which somewhat separates the gulars. Its forelobe is longer but nar rower than the hind lobe. The plastral formula is: abd > hum > fem > gul >< an > pect; the gulars are thickened and extend slightly beyond the carapacial rim. The bridge is wide; the inguinal is large and often subdivided, and the axillary is small to moderate. The plastron is yellowish brown with darkened seams, and some dark streaking may be present. The head is large with a nonprojecting snout and an upper jaw which lacks a hook, or is only slightly hooked. Its large prefrontal is longitudinally divided, and followed by a large undivided frontal scale; other head scales are small. The maxillae are ridged, but the premaxillae are not. The head is yellow to tan with pink pigment about the snout on some. Forelimbs are black; hind limbs and tail dark brown. The anterior surface of the somewhat flattened forelimbs is covered with large, overlapping pointed scales. A single large conical tubercle lies on each thigh, and the tail may end in a horny scale. (Ernst & Barbour 1989)Sexual dimorphism: Males have longer, thicker tails than do females. (Ernst & Barbour 1989)Testudo hermanni	Recognition: The rounded carapace (to 20 cm) is domed, highest behind the center, with abruptly descending sides, a slight cervical notch, and the posterior rim downturned and slightly serrated. A long narrow cervical scute is present. Vertebrals are broader than long; the 5th is expanded. Vertebral and pleural areolae are often raised and surrounded by growth annuli, giving the shell a lumpy appearance. The carapace is variable in color, ranging from yellow, olive, or orange to dark brown; lighter individuals contain variable amounts of dark blotching. The plastron is well developed a with a forelobe that is slightly upturned, tapered toward the front, and shorter and narrower than the hind lobe. The hind lobe bears a posterior notch. The plastral formula is: abd > hum > an >< gul > fem > pect; the paired gulars are thickened, but extend only slightly past the carapacial rim. The yellow bridge is broad, with a small axillary and small inguinal scute (which may be absent) that does not touch the femoral. The plastron is dark brown or black with a yellow border and midseam. The head is moderate in size with a nonprotruding snout and a hooked upper jaw. Its large prefrontal and frontal scales may be longitudinally divided or subdivided; other head scales are small. The head is brown or black; the chin may be lighter in color. Five to ten longitudinal rows of small, nonoverlapping scales lie on the anterior surface of each foreleg. The large scales on the heel are not greatly elongated, and there are no tubercles on the thighs. The tail has a large terminal scale. (Ernst & Barbour 1989)Sexual dimorphism: Males have longer, thicker tails with the vent near the tip. (Ernst & Barbour 1989) Geographic Variation: Two subspecies are recognized. Testudo hermanni hermanni Gmelin, 1789 is found in western Turkey, Bulgaria, southern Romania, Albania, Greece, Yugoslavia, southern Italy, and Sicily. It has a long (males 19, females 20 cm), flat, dull-colored carapace, and lacks a light spot behind and beneath each eye. T. h. robertmertensi Wermuth, 1952 lives in northwestern Italy, southern France, northeastern Spain, and on the Balearic Islands, Corsica, and Sardina. It is small (males 14 cm, females 16.5 cm), high domed, brightly colored with contrasting areas of yellow and black, and has a bright spot behind and beneath each eye. (Ernst & Barbour 1989)Testudo horsfieldii	Recognition: The rounded carapace (to 22 cm) is almost as broad as long and flattened dorsally (about twice as long as high). The highest point is near the center, and the sides are not abruptly descending. A weak cervical notch is present, and the posterior rim is not greatly flared, but may be slightly serrated. The cervical scute is usually long and narrow, but the vertebrals are all broader than long; the 5th is expanded. Areolae of the vertebral and pleural scutes are slightly raised and surrounded by growth annuli. There are usually 11 marginals on each side, and the supracaudal is undivided. The carapace ranges in color from totally light brown to yellowish brown with extensive dark-brown pigment on each scute. The plastron is well developed, but lacks the movable hinge between the abdominal and femoral scutes that occurs in other Testudo species. This has been considered a primitive character, but is more a likely a derived condition. The plastral forelobe is not upturned, tapers to the front, and is slightly longer and narrower than the hind lobe, which bears a posterior notch. The plastral formula is: abd> gul >< hum >< an > fem > pect; the paired gulars are thickened and extend slightly beyond the carapacial rim. The broad bridge has a small axillary and usually only a single small inguinal that does not touch the femoral. The bridge is usually yellow, but the plastron is black with yellow seams. The head is moderate in size with a nonprotruding snout and a hooked, often tricuspid upper jaw. Its large prefrontal is divided longitudinally; the frontal is large and usually undivided, and the other head scales are small. The head is yellowish brown with dark jaws. Limbs are also yellowish brown. Five or six longitudinal rows of large overlapping scales lie on the anterior surface of each foreleg. Spurlike scales are present on each heel, and blunt tubercles on each thigh. The tail ends in a horny claw. Males have longer, thicker tails with the vent close to the tip. (Ernst & Barbour 1989)Testudo graeca	Recognition: The rounded carapace (to 30 cm) is domed, highest behind the center, with abruptly descending sides, a broad cervical notch, and the posterior rim slightly to greatly flared and slightly serrated. The juvenile carapace may be slightly flattened. The cervical scute is generally long and narrow. Vertebrals are broader than long; the 5th is expanded, but narrower than the 4th (the 5th vertebral is much broader than the 4th in T. hermanni). Vertebral and pleural areolae are rarely raised, and the shell appears smooth compared to the lumpy T. hermanni. Eleven marginals lie on each side, a and a single undivided supracaudal scute is present. Carapacial color varies from yellow or tan with black or dark-brown blotching to totally gray or black. The plastron is well developed. Its forelobe is not or is only slightly upturned and gently tapers toward the front; it is shorter and narrower than the hind lobe, which bears a posterior notch. The plastral formula is: abd> hum >< gul >< an > pect > fem; the paired gular scutes are slightly thickened, but do not or only slightly extend beyond the carapacial rim. The bridge is broad, with a small axillary and one or two small or moderate inguinals that do not touch the femoral. Plastron and bridge are yellow to greenish yellow, brown, or gray, and usually with some dark-brown or black spotting on the plastron. The head is moderate in size with a nonprotruding snout and a weakly hooked, tricuspid upper jaw. Its prefrontal is rarely divided longitudinally, but the large frontal may be subdivided; other head scales are small. The head varies from yellow to brown, gray, or black, with or without dark spotting. Three to seven longitudinal rows of large, overlapping scales lie on the anterior surface of each foreleg. The heel may lack spurlike scales, but each thigh has very large, conical tubercle. The tail lacks a large terminal scale. Neck, limbs, and tail are yellowish brown to gray. Males have longer, thicker tails with the vent beyond the carapacial rim. (Ernst & Barbour 1989: 266)Geographic Variation: Multiple subspecies have been described.Testudo graeca graeca Linnaeus, 1758 lives in northern Africa from the Cyrenaica Peninsula of Libya westward along the Mediterranean Coast to Tunisia, Algeria and Morocco, and also on the Pityusae Islands of the Balearics, and in southern Spain. It is small (to 20 cm), flattened dorsally, lacks much expansion and flaring of the posterior marginals, and has a dark head.T. g. terrestris Forskal, 1775 ranges from eastern Libya and northern Egypt eastward through the Sinai Desert and Israel to Syria. It is small (to 20 cm), elevated dorsally, has some expansion but little flaring of the posterior marginals, and yellow pigmentation on the side and top of the head.T. g. ibera Pallas, 1814 occurs from northeastern Greece, Romania, Bulgaria, and Turkey eastward to the Transcaucasus of Russia and central Iran. It is larger (to 30 cm), is slightly flattened dorsally, has some expansion and slight flaring of the posterior marginals, and a unicolored tan or gray head.T. g. zarudnyi Nikolskii, 1896 is found only on the eastern part of the Central Iranian Plateau and adjacent Afghanistan. It is large (to 27.5 cm), elongated, and elevated dorsally, with much expansion, flaring, serration, and slight upturning of the posterior marginals, and a plain gray-brown head. (Ernst & Barbour 1989: 266)Description (T. perses): “T. perses is distinguished from all other taxa in the genus Testudo sensu stricto (in the sense of Gmira, 1995; Lapparent de Broin, 2000a, 2000b, 2001; Hervet, 2001; Perälä, 2002 in this volume), by the following combination of characters subject to individual variation and pertaining to adults and both sexes unless stated otherwise: Robustly built tortoise with a xiphiplastral hinge (showing xiphiplastral kinesis), ventrally short diagonal length of first costal, short fifth vertebral, dorsally wide supracaudal, very broad fourth vertebral and, with extremely long and wide anal scutes; anal midline seam (interanal) typically much longer than seam separating femorals; transverse seam separating humerals and femorals typically double-S-shaped, with or without a laterally straight proximal section; broad first vertebral; first vertebral almost always widest and sharp-edged anteriorly and, frequently elongated anteriorly in its proximal parts (modestly infundibular); fifth vertebral ventrally narrow; midbody (at bridge) of medium width relative to length, and rounded in dorsal view; in lateral view, outline of carapace mostly ventrally indented at anterior portion of first vertebral and, posteriormost marginals covering part of supracaudal (lateral outline of semi-adults can resemble that of T. kleinmanni); outline of carapace relatively angulate in anterior view, with perpendicular outermost (upper) surfaces of bridge marginals (i.e. lateral surfaces above the marginal crest which is well developed), edged upper arch (at costals) and relatively flat top with a slightly elevated proximal portion (central vertebral area); in posterior view the lower outline has a bell-shaped curvature due to marginal flaring, especially in males; carapace highest at slightly less than 2/3 length; supracaudal slightly flared to the rear, wide and almost box-shaped (rectangular) in females except for a vertically thin to more pronounced, laterally oriented and spiky offshoots towards the marginals in ventral corners, and with a more or less 90-100 degree inner angle between dorsolateral and dorsal sides; supracaudal of males more massive, usually flared to the rear (only rarely inverted) and also with ventrolateral offshoots, the inner angle between dorsolateral and dorsal sides being in the region of 90-120° and, with proximally elongated, smoothly U-shaped ventral extension becoming less apparent and more V-shaped towards the southeast of the range; outermost lateral extensions of bridge marginals (the crest separating dorsal and ventral portions of the scutes) typically in a 12-17 degree angle with respect to horizontal level, the open angle oriented cranially; inguinals relatively large, usually longer than broad, typically not touching femorals, and associated with smaller accessory scales (which may touch femorals); anterior and posterior free marginals flared to strongly flared, and serrated, convexly-rimmed towards the outside, and typically without much reversion; anteriormost (1st) marginals elongated, often protruding infront of second marginals; posteriormost (11th) marginals often extending posteriorly beyond supracaudal; lateral flaring of posterior marginals begins at, and is inclusive of, 8th marginal; 8th marginal featuring an anteriorly skewed, ventrally oriented half-dome to pyramid-shaped bulge with a more or less rounded apex and outer surface; greatest width at 8th or (more often) 9th marginals; anterior and posterior free marginals may extend beyond bridge marginals in dorsolateral (and ventrolateral) view, more so in males than in females; anterior plastron lobe ventrally convex in lateral view; nuchal scute (cervical) long and relatively narrow, and widest posteriorly or at around 3/4 length; gulars clearly set off from anterior lobe, and relatively long both ventrally and dorsally; length of bridge very variable, and not typically relatively shorter in males than in females (as opposed to most Testudo s. s.); anterior feet relatively massive and thick, featuring relatively long, almost drop-shaped, triangularish to four-edged scales with longest lateral sides facing claws, closely packed against the surface, and with generally not much overlap between scales; fore-feet with five relatively straight claws, the innermost of which are shorter than the rest, posterior extremities with four claws; tail relatively long, longer in males than in females, and very slender towards the tip; tip of tail features mostly a conspicuously enlarged, medium-sized twin-scale (not claw); upper thigh region typically with (at least) one horny spur on each thigh; thigh-spurs very broad at base; outline of open eyes in life more round than oval; bony carapace rim proximally convex towards the anterior; triturating surfaces of maxilla featuring only one longitudinal, modestly elevated central ridge; parietal bones straight or just very slightly notched in lateral view; supraoccipital crest (parietal-supraoccipital complex) long. (PERÄLÄ 2002) Basic coloration (perses, in alcohol): Ground colour of carapace and plastron from pale greenish-yellow (USNM 154515; subadult), to light or very dark-brown colour with a reddish or orange tinge (typical), or even completely grey or black. Plastron is usually not much darker than carapace. The yellowish variety “Golden Greek” is T. g. terrestris FORSKÅL 1775. (PERÄLÄ 2002)Markings (perses): Small juveniles (post-hatchlings) with a transverse dark band located centrally on 1st vertebral; 2nd to 5th vertebrals with small, more or less round central blotches with thin lateral offshoots of dark pigment not connected with the blotch. In lateral view, 1st costal features a horizontal dark stripe located at 1/3 height and running parallel to horizontal level; in 2nd and 3rd costals this band is also at 1/3 height, but it runs in a slight angle so that the posterior end is located highest. 4th costal has a central blotch. 2nd to 4th costals feature additionally centrally located vertical stripes at the anteriormost seams. Plastral markings may be completely absent, or there are tiny black blotches on the lower central region of the abdominals. Anterior marginals may feature dark semi-triangular markings. Bridge marginals with dark bands along anterior vertical borders. Posterior marginals with anterior and dorsal bands connected dorsolaterally. Larger juveniles and semi-adults: The central blotch on 1st vertebral divides laterally into two sister flecks. Costals may retain vertical bands near the anteriormost side of areolae, horizontal bands fade away or develope into larger, irregular blotches. Separately from these, extremely thin centrally oriented stripes appear at anterior and lateral, and anterior and ventrolateral borders of vertebrals and costals. These may develope into dark bands. The supracaudal may feature triangular lateral markings. These may later fade away, especially in the dorsal border region. Markings on marginals become darker and more defined. The plastron is irregularly pigmented with dark grey to blackish elements, darkest regions being located posterolaterally. Gulars and anals may be lighter coloured than other scutes. In adults, regions on and adjacent to the areolae seem to feature most pigmentation, dark blue-grey to black blotches with irregular borders. Markings around scute edges diffuse into centrally oriented rays which may or may not be connected to the central flecks. Dark blotches may appear on posterior ventral corners of (especially) the bridge marginals, or around the marginal crest. Many adult specimens are completely dark: grey, intensively dark-brown or black, with hardly any markings visible. Basic coloration of head and leg scutes varies from greenish-grey and grey to (as typical) light or deepish-dark chocolate-brown. The ground colour on most parts of the head is either uniform or it may feature blackish regions especially in the snout area, and darker brown to black, or, occasionally found yellowish scales towards the temple. Completely black heads are a rarity. The jaw region features often a dark grey to blackish triangular pattern, or a "Schnautzendreieck" sensu Eiselt & Spitzenberger (1967). Leg scutes have mostly a dark-brown, dark-violet to blackish tip, also on the hind legs. The base of leg scutes may be pale brown, pale grey or yellowish. Claws are light or dark chocolate-brown to dark violet and dark grey. Skin in soft parts is pale greyish, light brown or reddish-brown coloured. Eyes in life are very dark brown.” (PERÄLÄ 2002)Centrochelys sulcata	Recognition: This is the largest continental tortoise (76 cm), and is surpassed in size only by the island species from Aldabra and Galapagos. The oval carapace is flattened dorsally with abruptly descending sides, a deep cervical notch, both the anterior and posterior marginals serrated, and the posterior marginals upturned. No cervical scute is present. Vertebrals are broader than long; the 5th is smallest and somewhat expanded. Well-defined growth annuli surround the flat vertebral and pleural areolae. There are usually 11 marginals on each side, and a single undivided supracaudal scute which extends downward between the somewhat expanded posterior marginals. The carapace is uniformly brown. The plastron is well developed with a deep anal notch. Its forelobe tapers to the front, and the two bifurcated gulars project forward beyond the carapacial rim. Both plastral lobes are about the same length, but the forelobe is slightly broader. The plastral formula is: abd > hum > fem > gul > pect >< an. The wide bridge has two axillaries (the inner very small) and two inguinals (the inner small). Plastron and bridge are uniformly cream or yellow. The head is moderate with nonprotruding snout and a weakly hooked upper jaw. The large prefrontal scale is divided longitudinally and is followed by a large single frontal scale; other head scales are small. The head is brown with darker jaws; limbs and tail are also brown. The anterior surface of the forelimbs is covered with large, irregularly shaped, knobby, overlapping scales in three to six longitudinal rows. The hind surface of the thigh bears two or three large conical tubercles. The tail lacks a large terminal scale. The larger males have slightly longer, thicker tails and more concave plastra than do females, but the external sexual differences are slight. (Ernst & Barbour 1989)Geochelone platynota	Recognition: This rare tortoise is seldom seen outside of Burma, and, unfortunately, there it is usually eaten by the natives soon after being caught. The oval carapace (to 26 cm) is domed but flattened dorsally with descending sides and a slight cervical indentation; the posterior marginals are only slightly expanded and weakly serrated. No cervical scute is present. Vertebral is about as long as broad or occasionally longer, vertebrals 2-5 are broader than long; the 5th is expanded and the 4th relatively small. Well-defined growth annuli surround the flat vertebral and pleural areolae. There are usually 11 marginals on each side, and the supracaudal scute is undivided and downcurved. The carapace is dark brown or black with six or fewer radiating stripes extending from the yellow areola of each vertebral and pleural. Two yellow stripes form a V-shaped pattern on each marginal. The well-developed plastron is notched both anteriorly and posteriorly. Its forelobe is longer, but narrower than the hind lobe. The plastral formula is: abd > hum > fem > gul > an > pect; the pectoral scute is extremely narrow. The gulars are somewhat thickened, broader than long, and do not greatly extend anteriorly. The bridge is wide, and its axillary scute is smaller than the inguinal. Plastron and bridge are yellow, and each plastral a scute has a dark-brown or black blotch. The head is moderate with a nonprojecting snout and a weakly hooked, tricuspid upper jaw. The large prefrontal is divided longitudinally and is followed by a large single frontal scale; other head scales are small. Skin of the head, limbs, and tail is yellow to tan. The anterior surface of the forelimbs is covered with large pointed to rounded scales. The tail ends in a large horny scale. (Ernst & Barbour 1989)Sexual dimorphism: Males have longer, thicker tails with the vent nearer the tip. (Ernst & Barbour 1989)Testudo kleinmanni	Recognition: This species closely resembles Testudo graeca, and has in the past been considered a dwarf race of it. Its domed carapace (to 13.5 cm) is highest behind the center with abruptly descending sides, : cervical notch, and a flared supracaudal. Juveniles are dorsally flattened. A cervical scute is present which is usually long and narrow, but may be broad and triangular. Vertebrals are broader than long; the 5th is expanded. Vertebral and pleural areole may be raised slightly and surrounded by growth annuli. There are 10 to 12 marginals on each side; the supracaudal is usually undivided and projects beyond the marginals. The carapace is greenish yellow to yellowish brown, and usually has dark seam borders. The is plastron is well developed. Its forelobe is upturned, tapered anteriorly, and shorter and narrower than the hind lobe, which has a posterior notch. The plastral formula is: abd > an > pect >< hum gul > fem; the paired gulars are thickened, and rarely project beyond the carapacial rim. The broad bridge has an axillary and one or two small inguinal scutes, which may touch the femoral scute. Plastron and bridge are yellow with a central dark blotch on each abdominal scute and along the seams. The head iS moderate in size with a nonprotruding snout and a weakly hooked, tricuspid upper jaw. Its large prefrontal scale may be longitudinally divided or subdivided; the frontal may be entire or subdivided; other head scales are small. The quadrate almost, but not completely, encloses the stapes, and the orbito-nasal foramina are large. Head and limbs are yellowish brown; the jaws an. Three (occasionally four) longitudinal rows of large, non- overlapping scales lie on the anterior surface of each foreleg, and there are five claws on each forefoot. Spurlike scales occur on each heel, but no tubercles on the thighs. The tail lacks a terminal claw. Males have long tails with the vent toward the tip. (Ernst & Barbour 1989: 269)